Guide to the Trent history of medicine manuscripts collection, [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Trent History of Medicine manuscript collection [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980, (780 collections; approximately 6,000 items)
  - Massachusetts General Hospital Board of Trustees. Letter, 1816, May, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Circular letter, signed, soliciting contributions for the proposed institution from all towns within the Commonwealth. This exemplar is addressed to the town of Leicester and signed by Thomas H. Perkins, Daniel Sargent, Joseph May, Josiah Quincy, Tristram Barnard and Richard Sullivan.
  - Mather, Elisha. Papers, 1792-1799, (3 items) (Box 8)
    Physician of Lyme, Conn. Documents, unsigned. Statements of accounts with doctors Elisha and Samuel Mather.
  - Maton, William George, 1774-1835. Letter, 1809, Sept. 15, (1 item) (Box 8)
    English physician and botanist. Letter (ALS). Thanks Knowles for news received.
  - Matthey, André, b. 1779. Letter, 1814, Dec. 2, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Physician of Geneva. Letter (ALS). Matthey writes to Pacquin, the prison physician at Valence, of a Caesarian section operation and on obstetrics in general.
  - Mauban, Henri, b. 1873. Letter, 1914, June 3, (1 item) (Box 8)
    French physician. Letter (ALS). Submits, upon request, a bill for medical attendance.
  - Maugham, William Somerset, 1874-1965. Letters, 1956, (3 items) (Box 8)
    English novelist, playwright, and short-story writer. Two letters (TLS) from Maugham, 1 letter (TLS) from A. F. Searle, Maugham's secretary. Correspondence relates to Bett's biography, "Sir John Bland-Sutton".
  - May, Arthur, Sir. Photograph (copy), [After 1914], (1 item) (Box 8)
    Director-General, Naval Medical Service during World War I. Reproduction of a photo of Sir Arthur May in naval uniform.
  - Mayo, Herbert, 1796-1852. Letter, 1825, Apr. 24, (1 item) (Box 8)
    British physiologist and surgeon. Letter (ALS). Refers to Mayo's efforts to secure Davy's appointment as consulting surgeon at Yarmouth.
  - McClellan, George, 1796-1847. Papers, 1826, (3 items) (Box 8)
    Professor of surgery at the Jefferson Medical College. Letters of recommendation written by McClellan, for William Milnor, Jr., with Prof. Jacob Green; for Robert J. Dodd; and for George R. Morton, with John Eberle, Prof. Smith, B. Rush Rhees and John Baines.
  - McHenry, James, 1753-1816. Papers, 1780-1814 and undated, (4 items) (Box 8)
    Physician, pupil of Benjamin Rush, and politician. Letters (ALS) from John Morgan, on the court-martial of William Shippen, and from Hugh Williamson, relating to family matters. Papers include a draft of a bill, An act to regulate the medical establishment, and a holograph copy of a poem sent to the editor of the Morning Chronicle, on the occasion of the death of John B. Caldwell, McHenry's brother-in-law.
  - McKinley, Ida Saxton, 1847-1907. Letters, 1901-1907, (2 items) (Box 8)
    Wife of President William McKinley. Letters (ALS). Personal letters by Ms. McKinley to her former doctor, S. Weir Mitchell. In the first letter, written before her husband's assassination, she thanks Mitchell for a copy of his book "Hugh Wynne". In the second, she hopes that Mitchell will be able to visit Canton, Ohio, for the dedication of a memorial to her husband.
  - McNaughton, James, 1796-1874. Letter, [c. 1830], (1 item) (Box 8)
    Physician of New York. Letter (ALS). Recommends Dr. George W. Palmer for a position in the U.S. Navy. A note seconding McNaughton's recommendation added by Daniel Washburn.
  - Mead, Richard, 1673-1754. Papers, 1741-1748, (5 items) (Box 8)
    English physician, collector and classical scholar. Mead writes to Anthony Askew, during period of Askew's medical studies in Leyden and his tour of the Continent, on classical studies. Papers also include a document of a legal transaction between Mead and a Mr. Gore.
  - Mease, James, 1771-1846. Correspondence, 1796-1842, (10 items) (Box 8)
    Physician, scientist, philanthropist, and antiquarian of Philadelphia. Letters (ALS). Asks Rush to accept the enclosed check as payment of the teaching fee which Rush had waived for Mease in 1789. Mease also writes to John Jones of New York, on business matters; to Thomas Young of Savannah, on horticulture; to John Thompson, regarding the life of Charles Thomson; and to John F. Watson, with a reference to William D. Williamson.
  - Meigs, James Aitken, 1829-1879. Letter, 1876, Sept. 18, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Professor of physiology, Jefferson Medical College. Letter (ALS). Sends congratulations on the occasion of Loughlin's marriage.
  - Ménière, Prosper, 1799-1862. Document, 1836, Jan. 18, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Autograph document, signed. Attests that he attended a Madame Saussair for a rheumatic affection.
  - Mercantile Library Association. Records, 1834-1864, (22 items) (Box 8)
    Chiefly letters to officers of the Mercantile Library Association of New York City.
  - Meredith, Samuel, 1741-1817. Papers, 1775-1808, (22 items) (Box 8)
    Financier of Philadelphia. Papers include correspondence from John Jones, David Jackson and William Duncan, and statements of account with a dentist, physicians and pharmacists, including Andrew Spence, Philip S. Physick, Benjamin Rush, Nicholas Belleville, John Hart, John Ott and William Evans.
  - Meyraux, Pierre Stanislas, 1790-1832. Letter, 1830, Feb. 15, (1 item) (Box 8)
    French naturalist and anatomist. Letter (ALS). Applies for the position of tutor in zoology and botany at the preparatory school and submits his qualifications and publications. Addended is a letter of recommendation from the Baron de Villefosse.
  - Middleton, Peter, d. 1781. Document, 1754, Aug. 9, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Scottish physician in New York. Document, signed by Simon Johnson, recorder of New York. Bond to keep the peace brought by Dr. James Magra against Dr. Peter Middleton and Dr. William Farquhar.
  - Miller, Samuel. Letter, 1809, June 10, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Physician of Barbados. Letter (ALS). Asks to be appointed one of the Inoculators of the London Vaccine Institution and that an occasional supply of vaccine virus be delivered by packet boat to the island.
  - Millin, Aubin Louis, 1759-1818. Letter, 1806, Jan. 9, (1 item) (Box 8)
    French naturalist and antiquarian. Letter (ALS). Refers to the contents of a periodical, presumably the Magasin Encyclopédique, which he edited between 1795-1816.
  - Milman, Francis, Sir, 1746-1821. Letter, 1777, June 28, (1 item) (Box 8)
    English physician. Letter (ALS). Introduces the grandson of Richard Mead and son of Frank Nicholls. Briefly refers to Charles Blagden.
  - Milne-Edwards, H. (Henri), 1800-1885. Note, 1841, Aug. 4, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Belgian physician, naturalist and zoologist. Note (ANS). Sends an article.
  - Mitchell, John Kearsley, 1793-1858. Papers, 1827-1849, (7 items) (Box 8)
    Physician and scientist of Philadelphia. Mitchell corresponds with Oliver Wendell Holmes and Jacob Whitman Bailey regarding his book, On the Cryptogamous Origin of Malarious and Epidemic Fevers. Papers also include a line drawing, removed from Mitchell's son's copy of Gower's Lectures on the Diagnosis of Diseases of the Brain (1885); a letter of recommendation for Andrew Ellicott Kennedy; and printed sheet music, Oh! Fly to the Prairie, with lyrics by Mitchell.
  - Mitchill, Samuel L. (Samuel Latham), 1764-1831. Correspondence, 1792-1928, (15 items) (Box 8)
    Physician and naturalist. Letters (ALS). Letters to surgeon Valentine Mott, horticulturalist William Robert Prince, to auditor and naturalist William Lee relate to natural history. Papers also include verses from Le Brun dedicated to Mitchill by Francesca Pascalis and a letter to her from her father, Felix Pascalis Ouviere. Mitchill also receives a letter of introduction from Robert Vaux. In 1928 Mary Mayes writes Dr. Braislin regarding the sale of Mitchill papers in her possession.
  - Moffatt, Thomas. Letter, 1747, Aug. 22, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Surgeon to the Canada Forces raised in the colony of Rhode Island during King George's War. Letter (ALS). Moffatt asks to be reimbursed for personal expenditures in the acquisition of medical supplies.
  - Moore, John, 1729-1802. Letter, 1797, (1 item) (Box 8)
    English physician and writer. Letter (ALS). Writes on his novels Zeluco and Edward. On the reverse is a note that the letter was received of Captain Graham Moore, 1798, May 16.
  - Morgagni, Giambattista, 1682-1771. Papers, 1760-1941, (2 items) (Box 8)
    Italian physician and anatomist. Autograph dedication in Italian by Morgagni. On the reverse of this is a note in German by Sigismund Breit. A letter in English from the Army Medical Library authenticates the signature to be that of Morgagni.
  - Morgan, Daniel, 1736-1802. Document, 1787, July 5, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Physician. Autograph receipt, signed, of payment from Robert Carter for the medical service rendered to one of his slaves by a Mrs. Frances Morgan.
  - Morgan, John. Letter, 1833, June 17, (1 item) (Box 8)
    British physician. Letter (ALS). Petitions for the institution of Welsh language instruction in schools and the use of the Welsh language in courts and churches in those areas where the majority of the populace speaks only Welsh.
  - Morse, Edward Sylvester, 1838-1925. Correspondence, 1883 and undated, (2 items) (Box 8)
    U.S. zoologist and director of the Peabody Museum. Letters (ALS) from Morse relating to his collection of Japanese pottery. Attached is an undated newspaper clipping regarding a lecture delivered by Morse at the Lowell Institute. Morse was professor of zoology at the Imperial University, Tokyo, between 1877-1880.
  - Morton, Samuel George, 1799-1851. Letter, 1845, Aug. 26, (1 item) (Box 8)
    U.S. physician, anatomist and zoologist. Letter (ALS). Writes about his publications Synopsis of the Organic Remains of the Cretaceous Group and Crania Americana.
  - Morton, W. T. G. (William Thomas Green), 1819-1868. Letter, 1853 and undated, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Physician, one of the first to discover the anesthetic properties of ether. Letter (ALS) to Benjamin Perley Poore and James Mandeville Carlisle.
  - Moseley, W. H. Letter, 1816, Jan. 15, (1 item) (Box 8)
    English military physician. Letter (ALS). Writes of his arrival in Germany and of the English military medical service in general.
  - Mott, Valentine, 1785-1865. Papers, 1806-1863 and undated, (10 items) (Box 8)
    New York surgeon. Autograph letters and documents, signed. Includes letters to his father and brother from England, on British politics towards the United States and on the Continent; to Dr. Pollock informing him that he is unable to find a copy of his (Mott's) eulogy on Dr. John Revere; letters of recommendation; and receipts.
  - Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871. Papers, 1857 and undated, (3 items) (Box 8)
    British geologist. Letters (ALS) dated 1857 on his publishers and his works and two samples of his signature.
  - Musgrave, William, 1655?-1721. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 8)
    English physician and antiquarian. Holograph letter, unsigned. Musgrave writes to Moyle on the Roman remains in Belga, a district of Roman Britain. The letter is in Latin.
  - Myers, Thomas, 1774-1834. Letter, 1827, June 28, (1 item) (Box 8)
    British mathematician and geographer. Letter (ALS). Names an essay on African society as his choice for the prize essay.
  - Nansen, Fridtjof, 1861-1930. Letter, 1909, Sept. 21, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Norwegian zoologist and oceanographer. Letter (TLS). Regretfully declines invitation to write an article.
  - Napheys, George Henry, 1842-1876. Manuscript, [1870s], (1 item) (Box 8)
    U.S. physician. Salesman's instructions for presenting Naphey's book, The Prevention and Cure of Disease.
  - Nélaton, Auguste, 1807-1873. Letter, [Between 1836 and 1873], (1 item) (Box 8)
    French surgeon. Letter (ALS). Prescribes treatment of a fistula on a joint by iodized injections, Burgrave dressings and sea baths.
  - Newport Botanic Thomsonian Infirmary. Broadside, [After 1836], (1 item) (Box 8)
    Broadside, no illustrations. Detailed advertisement for health institution in Newport, Rhode Island, at the "corner of Mill and Spring Streets." With testimonials from Benjamin Waterhouse, Thomas Hersey, and others. C. Gardner's name appears as "Botanic Physician, Agent for Dr. Samuel Thompson." Printed by Jas. Atkinson.
  - Newton, Charles. Document, 1820, Dec. 16, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Dentist from Massachusetts. Holograph document, signed. Receipt of payment for set of dentures.
  - Nightingale, Florence, 1820-1910. Correspondence, 1870-1941 and undated, bulk 1870-1897, (14 items) (Box 8)
    British nurse and hospital and health care reformer. Papers include letters to William Howell Reed, thanking him for the gift of his Hospital Life in the Army of the Potomac (1866); to Lady Marian Alford, relating to the Lord Stratford de Redcliffe Memorial Fund; and a series of personal and very affectionate letters to Miss A. P. Lemon, later Mrs. L. Roscoria, a colleague and personal friend, regarding her health, as well as the illness of her mother, and affairs of the hospital. Other items are newspaper clippings about Nightingale and a postcard bearing her portrait.
  - North, Elisha, 1771-1843. Manuscript, [After 1811], (1 item) (Box 8)
    U.S. physician. Manuscript pages from a proposed, but never published second and revised edition of North's book, A Treatise on a Malignant Epidemic, Commonly called Spotted Fever. Available are photographs of the title page of North's own copy of the book, which bears marginal notes in his hand. Reader is referred to the article by Pleadwell, "A new view of Elisha North ... ", in Annals of Medical History, 6 (1924). The manuscript and North's copy form the basis of this essay.
  - Norton, Rupert, 1867-1914. Correspondence, 1909-1912, (2 items) (Box 8)
    Editor of the Johns Hopkins Hospital Bulletin and reports. Letters (ALS) to Norton, from Canadian physician Sir James Alexander Grant (1831-1920), thanking him for the kindness shown during a visit to Baltimore, and from Canadian gynecologist John Clarence Webster, agreeing to write a review.
  - Norton, William Augustus, 1810-1883. Letter, 1851, July 23, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Professor of natural philosophy and civil engineering at Brown and Yale Universities. Letter (ALS). Writes of texts and supplies for the civil engineering class at Brown University.
  - Nothnagel, Hermann, 1841-1905. Letter, 1876, June 9, (1 item) (Box 8)
    German physician. Letter (ALS).
  - Nott, Josiah Clark, 1804-1873. Note, [Between 1820 and 1873], (1 item) (Box 8)
    Physician and ethnologist of South Carolina. Note (ANS). Inquires about appropriate attire for an evening engagement.
  - Nussbaum, Johann Nepomuk, Ritter von, 1829-1890. Letter, 1866, Oct. 29, (1 item) (Box 8)
    German surgeon. Letter (ALS). Objects to the slanders against him printed in the "Neuesten Nachrichten" and in other papers.
  - Okie, Abraham Howard. Papers, 1842-1868 and undated, (10 items) (Box 8)
    Homeopathic physician of Rhode Island. Papers include letters from Dixon Hall Lewis and, in German, from Constantine Hering; prescriptions; and notes relating to social engagements.
  - Oliver, William, 1695-1764. Letter, 1758, Jan. 7, (1 item) (Box 8)
    English physician and philanthropist. Letter (ALS). Discusses the state of health of his patient, the Duchess of Newcastle, and his use of the Bath waters in her treatment.
  - Olivier, M. Correspondence, 1921-1922, (2 items) (Box 8)
    French psychiatrist. Two letters (ALS). Asks that recipient permit Lallemand, Olivier's former intern, incorporate recipient's clinical notes and observations into his thesis for the Centre Neurologique at Montpellier.
  - Olmade, Jean-Théodore. Letter, 1829 Nov. 3, (1 item) (Box 8)
    French physician and author. Short letter in French written from Paris. Seems to be social in nature.
  - Olmsted, Denison, 1791-1859. Letter, 1838, Sept. 22, (1 item) (Box 8)
    Physician and professor of Connecticut. Letter (ALS). Accepts the vice presidency of the American Institute of Instruction from Cushing, a Boston merchant and philanthropist.
  - Ordronaux, John, 1830-1908. Papers, 1879, (3 items) (Box 8)
    Physician and lawyer of New York. Two letters (ALS) and a newspaper clipping. Ordronaux, then State Commissioner in Lunacy, writes to William Fairfield Warren, president of Boston University, that he must postpone his lectures in law at Boston University. He attaches a newspaper clipping which relates that a report critical of the management of the State Lunatic Asylum had been presented, but that the signatures of the doctors presenting the report had apparently been forged.
  - Orfila, Matthieu Joseph Bonaventure, 1787-1853. Papers, 1841-1842, (2 items) (Box 8)
    Physician, chemist and toxicologist. Letters (ALS). Letters of recommendation for a M. Tinville and a M. Gatteaux. The second letter is addressed to the Comte de Rambuteau and is co-signed by M. Cordier and M. Lavoint.
  - Osler, William, Sir, 1849-1919. Correspondence, 1902-1917, (13 items) (Box 8)
    Physician, book collector and medical historian. Mostly letters (ALS and TLS) and a typed note, unsigned. Osler's correspondents include Arnold C. Klebs, S. Weir Mitchell, W. Fleming, Mrs. Parmelee, and Charles Loomis Dana. Letters relate to personal, family and professional affairs and Osler's interest in medical history.
  - Owen, David Dale, 1807-1860. Letter, 1852, June 10, (1 item) (Box 9)
    U.S. geologist. Letter (ALS). Writes regarding arrangements for the proofreading of Parry's botanical report, to be published after his own geological report on the Northwest.
  - Owen, Richard, 1804-1892. Correspondence, 1837-1850, (3 items) (Box 9)
    British zoologist and anatomist. Owen sends a report on a lecture on New Zealand birds to a Miss Bailey and wishes a Mr. Pearson professional success in Lancaster. The electrician Andrew Crosse writes to Owen of the discovery of insects in metallic solutions supposed to be destructive to organic life.
  - Oxley, W. W. Letter, 1880, Feb. 10, (1 item) (Box 9)
    Letter (ALS). Informs a Miss Buck that he must leave early and that she should postpone her visit.
  - Oyntment of Tobacca... [single sheet with three prescriptions], undated, (1 item) (Box 9)
    Medical receipt in an anonymous hand. The first page is a recipe for "Dr. Meads emultion for the lungs." On the verso, in a different hand, are two additional receipts: "Oyntment of tobacca" and "Lucutellus oyntment or balsome".
  - Péan, Jules-Émile, 1830-1898. Note, 1893, Jan. 6, (1 item) (Box 9)
    French surgeon. Note (ANS). Informs addressee that he will be detained by an operation and thus will not be able to meet at the appointed time.
  - Page, Richard Channing Moore, 1841-1898. Letter, 1889, Jan. 18, (1 item) (Box 9)
    Physician and historian. Letter (ALS). Responds to Green's request for the autograph of J. C. Breckinridge. Page served on Breckinridge's staff during the Civil War.
  - Paget, James, Sir, 1814-1899. Papers, 1880-1898, (6 items) (Box 9)
    British surgeon and physiologist. Letters (ALS) relating to social engagements and to the anti-vivisection movement. A letter from Victor Horsley refers to Paget's lectures On the cause of the rhythmic motion of the heart.
  - Paget, Stephen, 1855-1926. Papers, 1908 and undated, (2 items) (Box 9)
    British surgeon. Letters (ALS). Paget writes a cordial personal letter to a Dr. Ewens. Sir Frederick Treves writes Paget regarding the Research Defence Society.
  - Panas, Ph., 1832-1903. Letter, 1880, July 26, (1 item) (Box 9)
    Greek physician who practiced in Paris. Letter (ALS). Prescribes a course of treatment in a gynecological case.
  - Pancoast, Joseph, 1805-1882. Letter, 1861, Apr. 22, (1 item) (Box 9)
    Surgeon and anatomist in Philadelphia. Letter (ALS). A letter of recommendation for a former student, Dr. Bertolet.
  - Pariset, Etienne, 1770-1847. Letter, 1826, Mar. 20, (1 item) (Box 9)
    French physician. Letter (ALS). Inquires about an occurrence of yellow fever.
  - Parker, Willard, 1800-1884. Letter, 1866, Aug. 10, (1 item) (Box 9)
    U.S. surgeon and professor of surgery. Letter (ALS). Responds to an inquiry about family genealogy.
  - Parrish, Joseph, 1779-1840. Document, 1817, May 17, (1 item) (Box 9)
    Physician of Philadelphia. Autograph document, signed. Certificate gives age, residence and illness of a William Stevenson.
  - Parrish, Joseph, 1818-1891. Letter, 1888, Feb. 16, (1 item) (Box 9)
    Physician of Burlington, New York. Letter (ALS). Sends pamphlets on alcoholism and the medical jurisprudence of alcoholism.
  - Parsons, Usher, 1788-1868. Correspondence, 1819-1840, (15 items) (Box 9)
    U.S. naval surgeon. Letters (ALS). Personal and professional correspondence includes letters from R.N.D. Desgenettes, Jeffries Wyman, John Jeffries, John Collins Warren, James Thacher, Thomas M. Potter, George Hayward, John Witt Randall, Enoch Hale, John White Webster, Jerome van Crowninshield Smith, John D. Fisher, James Jackson and J.B. Whitridge. Also includes a letter from Parsons to his brother-in-law, Oliver Wendell Holmes.
  - Partridge, Richard, 1805-1873. Letter, 1837, May 6, (1 item) (Box 9)
    Surgeon of King's College Hospital. Letter (ALS). Request for student tickets to the college lectures.
  - Pascalis Ouviere, Felix, 1762-1833. Letter, 1824, Dec. 25, (1 item) (Box 9)
    French physician and epidemiologist. Letter (ALS). Argues that his proposals regarding the stocks and stockholders of the New York Horticultural Society have been misconstrued.
  - Pascalis, Pierre Antoine. Papers, 1819 and 1821, Feb. 22, (2 items) (Box 9)
    French physician who wrote several books on lung diseases and electricity as a medical treament. Letter in French from Pascalis to a Baron regarding his nomination to the associates of the Academy. Translated into English. Accompanied by a small volume written by Pascalis.
  - Pasquier, __. Papers, 1872-1873, (2 items) (Box 9)
    Pharmacist in Chatelet. Letters (ALS) to M. Lebon, President of the Royal Academy of Medicine of Belgium. Letters annotated by Lebon.
  - Pasteur, Louis, 1822-1895. Papers, 1877-1889 and undated, (5 items) (Box 9)
    French physician and chemist. Papers include a letter requesting the transfer of a relative; a note on his work on rabies; autograph manuscript notes on a text by Edouard Dumas, which refer to incorrect calculations in Lavoisier's work; and six pages of holograph manuscript notes, corrected by Pasteur, on the proceedings of the Academy of Medicine, Paris, March 19, 1878, which relate to his work on anthrax.
  - Pattison, Granville Sharp, 1791-1851. Letter, 1835, Apr. 21, (1 item) (Box 9)
    Scottish physician and professor of surgery, practiced and taught in Philadelphia and Baltimore. Letter (ALS). Asks for the renewal of a note for $750.00.
  - Payne, Alban Smith. Letter, 1888, Dec. 11, (1 item) (Box 9)
    Physician of Virginia. Letter (ALS). Gives various details about his life, citing correspondents of note and relating his part in the "Willie Patterson affair", in which Payne knocked down Patterson, apparently a prizefighter, for attacking Usher Parsons.
  - Peabody, Nathaniel, 1741-1823. Letter, 1814, June 25, (1 item) (Box 9)
    Letter (ALS). Communicates Estwick Evans' request for blank writs and summons. A typed transcript is available.
  - Pelletan, Philippe Jean, 1747-1829. Document, 1827, July 3, (1 item) (Box 9)
    French surgeon and professor of surgery. Autograph document, signed. Attests to the state of physical health of one Jean Baptiste St. Pichon.
  - Pennsylvania Hospital (Philadelphia, Pa.). Papers, 1778-1819, (4 items) (Box 9)